It's the US military's most sacred
mission.
Mounted [music] Army soldiers transport
the remains of fallen service members to
their final [music] resting place in
Arlington National Cemetery.
Today, only 27 soldiers are qualified
for the role.
Many start off with no [music] riding
experience.
To get here, they have to endure [music]
more than 4 months of training.
>> If you keep riding 2 m over left, you
end up in the wrong funeral.
>> And it all comes down to one final test.
Instructors grade the riders' form and
posture.
And one wrong move could mean failure.
>> [music]
>> We went inside their training to find
out what it takes to be a horse soldier
in the US [music] Army Caisson
Detachment.
Soldiers who pass the first [music] 12
weeks of basic horsemanship training
move on to the final phase.
Six [music] weeks of advanced
instruction in Ocala, Florida, known as
the horse capital of the world. Army
soldiers train at Live Oak Stud, a 4,500
acre farm owned by the [music] family of
Chester Weber, an heir to the Campbell
Soup fortune.
>> So, my great-grandfather started the
Campbell Soup Company. [music] I'm not a
maker of soup other than as a hobby.
>> Weber is an accomplished [music]
equestrian athlete, having won 23
national championships in the sport of
four-in-hand carriage driving.
>> Three reds in his mouth. This horse
>> In 2024, [music]
the Army hired Weber to assemble a
world-class team to train the soldiers.
Like their riding instructor, Inga Kahn.
>> Find your spot. I want straight lines. I
need space between my horses. I'm not
happy. If you turn too late, you will
bounce into each other. Too early won't
hurt you. Too late will hurt you. Nice
soft trot.
>> I just I just misunderstood what you
were saying.
>> Good.
That's because I'm German.
I grew up as a daughter of a horse
trainer, so I was riding before I was
born.
I I was always into horses my whole
life. Center line, boys. Manse, are you
with me?
>> Ma'am.
>> Good.
>> Caisson Detachment candidates are
selected based on their discipline,
[music]
composure, and physical fitness. Most of
the soldiers arrive with little or no
experience with horses.
>> Your work horse is the fourth.
>> Yeah, first off.
>> What's that like?
>> It's was scary at first, but now I get
used to it. It's all the training, so.
>> Turn. Turn. No.
Don't wait. When we do it perfect, and I
want it perfect, then the center line is
going to be between Roberts and Sims.
>> She's very strict, [music] and that's
one thing I like about her cuz I don't
want some trainer that's like not going
to tell me what I need to work on, and
she gets
>> [music]
>> She's on my tail 24/7.
>> Specialist Jamie Sims is the only woman
in the squad.
>> What's that like?
>> Um I I think it's kind of normal. I was
At my old company, so I was the only
female, too. So, I kind of got used to
it.
It kind of helped having like the
trainers that are females.
>> Where are you, Sims? You are like 2 m
over to the left. If you keep riding 2 m
over left, you end up in the wrong
funeral. Division, volte.
March.
We are starting with putting the boys
into the correct posture and in the
correct position and helping them
finding balance in case if something
happens this horse spook to the side or
gets a little faster or slower that they
don't get out of balance. And when we
achieve this, we start to ride in
sections. So, we ride behind each other.
When they can do this, we put them
pair-wise together and let them ride in
formation. Wait. Everybody needs to work
together. Since this was the mistake you
did from the beginning on, we deleted
this mistake totally. You never did it
again.
Now you're doing it again. I don't want
it. I give you 4 and 1/2 from 10 points.
That could be better.
>> A person like that, they really do care
about you. They want you to succeed and,
you know, look great on a horse. So, I
don't blame her for being, you know,
hard on us. If a person really cares,
they're going to be hard.
>> 23-year-old [music]
Sergeant Nick Cardinas joined the Army
in 2022 as a motor transport operator.
>> Before joining caisson, I had zero horse
experience. I I knew nothing. So, I just
[music] started asking questions,
started seeing guys what they were doing
on a daily basis. And over time, it just
I started flowing like water.
>> You need to react quick. Quick.
>> [music]
>> Quick. When the mistakes happen, you
pick it up. When they come in,
uh you go, "Okay, good. This going to be
hard and maybe we're not going to make
it and
>> [music]
>> but I learned now say, "Chill.
It's going to be fine. I'm very
confident [music] they get all through
and we'll be fine."
Way better. We work the horse. Say
they're all good. They're all good. Good
horse.
>> Learning to ride one horse is
challenging enough.
But the soldiers also train on a
six-horse hitch, the formation that
pulls the wagon carrying the casket
known as the caisson.
>> Caisson,
halt.
>> When you're going left, get over to the
right. When you're going right, get over
to the left. Okay? Always check your own
I know it seems like that's not a
problem through there, but it it it
looks bad. Always Always check your
equipment.
>> To train soldiers on the caisson,
Chester Weber hired David Saunders, who
worked as a coachman for the British
royal family.
>> I was Duke of Edinburgh's coachman. I
worked for the Queen and I was served at
Her Majesty's pleasure for 20 years. I
told you yesterday the horses have got
to cuddle up against each other. The
horses are green and the drivers are
green, the riders. They've just learned
to ride, so it's all
a magical mystery tour. The lead, if you
don't give him enough room, you're
screwed. Okay, gentlemen,
at your leisure, follow me.
They have to be spatially aware cuz it's
all about starting, stopping, and
steering. Three golden rules of doing
postilion.
>> In the postilion riding style, each
soldier rides one horse while guiding a
second with their right hand.
>> Good job.
>> Riders train on both a smaller wagon and
the longer caisson, which requires much
wider turns.
>> Good job. Look before you turn. Look
before you turn. Take control, wheel
man. Take control.
>> There are three roles on the six-horse
hitch that pulls the caisson. The rider
in the front is the lead. The rider in
the middle is the swing. And the rider
in the back is the wheel.
The team works together to start, stop,
and turn, training on an obstacle
course.
>> All together, girls. So, all together.
>> The course includes tighter turns than
the horses would ever see at Arlington,
plus ground obstacles like pool noodles
and hula hoops placed throughout.
[music]
>> This is nothing to simulate how they're
going to do in a funeral, but if they
can do all this, then the funerals will
be a piece of cake.
>> It's kind of nerve-wracking because now
it's higher stakes. Like, it's training
right now, but then you have to also
think, "Okay, this is real life
missions. Like, we can't mess anything
up."
>> For decades, the horses pulled a heavy
artillery style wagon that weighed
nearly 3,000 lb.
In 2025, the Army introduced a
redesigned caisson that weighs less than
half as much as the previous model and
has a price tag of $256,000.
Today, more than 400,000 [music] people
are buried at Arlington National
Cemetery.
The caisson detachment supports up to 10
[music] funerals each week for select
service members. For 75 years, [music]
the unit was synonymous with one of the
military's most sacred traditions, but
in 2023, [music]
the Army shut the program down.
>> The Army says it is suspending the use
of its military horses following reports
the horses are living in unhealthy
conditions.
>> The deaths of multiple Army horses
exposed unsanitary conditions and a lack
of open space for grazing. During the
suspension, more than 2,000 Arlington
funerals [music] took place without
horses.
The program returned [music] in 2025
thanks to the Army's investment of over
$30 million
to build new facilities and revamp
[music] training. That's why the Army
called Chester Weber.
>> You get there? He said, "Okay, so when
are you moving to Haymarket, Virginia to
help us with this program?" I said,
"Hold on a second, guys. And there's no
moving to Haymarket, Virginia, but I'll
make you a deal. If you guys come down
to Ocala, Florida, I'd be more [music]
than happy to help put together a team
of fantastic people to bring excellence
and perspective back to the program."
>> The Army also put a horse veterinarian
in command of the unit.
>> As we look at this and really kind of
put the animal first and really put the
animal welfare piece of it um front and
center, it puts a a different outlook on
it than just solely completing [music]
the missions. Really completing the
mission and actually more of the way we
do it and you know, putting the horses
first.
The soldiers are the primary people
[music] that actually tell us like,
"Hey, something's wrong." We're seeing
them all the time. They can pick up on
those little the little telltale signs
where rather than treating an illness,
we're trying to prevent it before it
happens.
>> [music]
>> The soldiers are responsible for taking
care of the horses.
>> You worked hard today. You got all
sweaty.
>> Feeding them,
cleaning their hooves,
and bathing them.
>> [music]
>> Taking care of horses is a lot of work.
>> It depends on what you define as a lot
of work. Some of it could be a little
bit tedious, but once you get in a
rhythm, once you just take things step
by step, it's not it's not too bad.
>> Would you call horses high maintenance?
>> Yes.
>> Absolutely.
They're absolutely high maintenance.
>> All of them have their own like little
personalities and you can see that in
their ears, their eyes, their facial
expressions, everything.
>> [music]
>> Most of the horses used by the Caisson
Detachment [music]
are Percherons, a breed known for its
strength, endurance, [music]
and calm temperament.
But they're prey animals, instinctively
[music]
wired to flee from danger. Just one
spooked horse can disrupt a military
funeral. So, they're trained to remain
[music] steady
in an unpredictable environment.
>> [crying]
>> Former law enforcement officer Casey
Farrell's specialty is desensitization.
>> So, my role here is to teach the horse
that if something scary comes in real
life when they are doing their duty back
in Virginia, is to stay calm and relaxed
and then also teach the soldiers how to
handle that.
>> During training, an air cannon goes off
without warning.
Exposing the horses to the kinds of
sudden noises they may encounter during
a military funeral.
>> Yeah, just relax. Who cares about a
cannon? If you don't care, the horses
don't care.
>> So, it's an air cannon. It nothing comes
out of it. It's just gas. Most people
tend to when they hear a big scary
noise, they tense up.
And when we're relaxed as riders, then
the horses relax as well.
>> There's a bang. We don't want the horses
to run away. So, they've got to be
expect a bang all the time. So, it's for
both of them. So, they don't their
pants. But, don't put that on the film.
>> That's hard to turn.
>> Good job.
>> [music]
>> A speaker placed by the obstacle course
plays loud music and simulated sounds of
vehicles and other loud noises.
>> [music]
>> They're going to hear a lot of drums.
They're going to hear a lot of sirens,
gunshots, birds. So, it just simulates
anything that they're going to hear.
So, I can just call it the noise maker.
It's just a metal paint can. It's got
rocks. It's got screws. It's got
pennies. It's got all of that.
We were trying to figure out what can
simulate the noise of a casket going on
and off.
Any of that so those horses get used to
it.
>> Back in the barn, the soldiers wave
flags in front of horses in the stalls
to desensitize them to sudden movement
and noise.
>> Happy birthday to you.
>> As training comes to an end in Florida,
Sergeant Cardenas celebrates his 24th
birthday.
>> Happy birthday to you.
>> The party in [music] Florida may be
coming to an end, but this squad's
biggest challenge lies ahead.
Six weeks later, they're back in
Virginia training for their final test
[music] known as validation. It's where
we ran into a soldier just
his time with the Caisson Detachment who
turned out to be a familiar face.
Specialist Derrick Beasley, a sentinel
at the Tomb [music] of the Unknown
Soldier, we met while filming an episode
of Boot Camp in 2025.
After reaching [music] the pinnacle of
one elite Army role, he's starting at
the bottom of another.
>> I finished my required time at the tomb
and I wanted to stay in this area and
continue working in the cemetery and and
honoring the dead like I did at the
tomb, perfect mission here.
>> Inside Arlington, soldiers conduct
training rides through the cemetery to
familiarize the horses and themselves
with the environment.
Soldiers known as section workers follow
closely to clean up after the horses.
>> Everything has a part to play, you know,
there's always a bigger picture. So, you
know, some people have an attitude
towards it like, "Oh, why did I enlist
for this?" You're like, "Hey, you're
doing this because there's a purpose
behind this."
>> The horses are connected to the wagon
using a complex system of harnesses,
straps, and reins known as tack. The
total cost for all of the tack used for
the six-horse hitch is about $160,000.
Before they ride in funeral missions,
all soldiers have to pass the validation
test. Today, Specialist Sims and
Sergeant Cardenas are getting their
chances.
Held in a parking lot, the test
simulates the Caisson's role in a
funeral.
>> Ready. Step.
>> Riders are graded on their form,
posture, and their ability to control
the horses if distractions arise.
>> They're feeling the pressure right now.
They're nervous because it's the one
thing that you're here at Caisson to do,
but they they have all the training they
need and they're fully capable.
>> Ready? Go.
>> Things were going smoothly
until the horses came to a stop.
The instructors grade the riders on how
they handled the situation.
The test is over.
>> Do you think you passed?
>> [sighs and gasps]
>> No, I don't think I passed.
>> I feel like it went okay. Besides the
end, the end was a a little rough. So,
let's see what happens.
>> So, if they pass this validation,
they're going to go into the cemetery
and conduct military funerals with
escort. If they don't pass, it's back to
the drawing board for a couple weeks.
They'll get back into the training
process and they'll they'll try again.
>> So, for the first iteration on lead with
Cardenas,
uh you did pass. Whenever the horse is
back, you corrected them. You weren't
egregious with it, so good job on your
your part.
Sims,
uh so, you did not pass.
Um reason being is because you had
dropped the off reins at one point.
Landino went to go call a Caisson
forward ho, and before he could, you had
to gather your off reins. And then at
one point, your foot did come out of the
stirrup. Just make sure that you're
keeping your feet in the stirrup. If
something were to go wrong, you at least
you're maintaining one foot in the
stirrup.
>> All right. Good job today, guys.
>> [music]
>> They said everything was good. It was
just like one safety hazard that I had
my reins
and I didn't have control of my horse at
one point. I didn't think it was a
safety hazard, but honestly, they've
done this way longer than I have. I'm
like I'm new to it.
I have high standards to myself. I'm
really strong-headed and like I talked
to my sergeant and I was like, "So,
when's the next validation?" cuz I was
like, "I'm ready for it." Like I know
what I need to
do and not do. I just have to wait see
what happens.
>> According to the Caisson Detachment,
Specialist Sims is still waiting to
attempt her second validation test.
>> [music]
>> Feel amazing. I can't wait to start. It
has been a long road. I didn't I didn't
think I was going to make it this far,
you know, through all the training and
the prep. It definitely paid off today.
>> [music]
>> Today, Sergeant Cardenas rides in the
lead position on an actual funeral
mission in Arlington [music] National
Cemetery.
>> It's a very indescribable experience
because months and months of training,
just the amount of weight on your
shoulders just lets off, but the
experience like doing the missions,
it's humbling. It's It's a great
experience.
>> This funeral honored [music] Air Force
Lieutenant Henry J. Carlin, who was
killed in a plane crash during World War
II.
>> [music]
>> After being declared missing in action
for nearly 80 years, scientists [music]
used DNA analysis to identify his
remains.
>> [music]
>> Emotions were all over the place. It
didn't feel real, but at the same time
you're just you're doing your job.
>> [music]
>> We only get one entrance in the
cemetery, one experience, so I wish I
could relive it again.
>> Filming for this [music] story began on
March 2nd, 2026.
The third day of the war [music] with
Iran.
And one day after the first American
troops were [music] killed in an Iranian
drone strike in Kuwait.
Those killed in action qualify for
burial at Arlington with full caisson
honors.
>> When you look at things that are
happening overseas, it helps you to
really put in perspective what we're
actually doing. We're taking them to
their final resting place. That's why
it's important that we do it correctly.
>> Caissons.
Halt.
>> The weight of this job is very
significant to me.
Uh means a lot. So, to be able to do
this is something that I really like
sits heavy [music] with me. And just
makes me give that extra push to do this
job to the best of my ability.